Finding Aid for Student Government Council (University of Michigan) records, 1912-1976
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Student Government Council (University of Michigan) records 1912-1976
University of Michigan. Student Government Council.
87325 Bimu F13 2
Records, 1912-1975, of the Student Government Council and predecessor student government agencies at the University of Michigan. Contains minutes, clippings and topical files concerning, in part, black studies and black student organizations. Also papers of Laing Study Committee, a university group concerned with the study and evaluation of student government.
11 linear feet
1 oversize folders
3 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were acquired in multiple accessions (donors nos. 1404, 2897, and 5705 ).
The record group is open without restriction.
The first student government at the University of Michigan was organized as the Student Council in 1906 by the Michigan Union. The Union itself had been organized in 1903 by students wishing to bring unity to an exponentially growing student body who had no common dormitory or social space.
The need for self-governance was recognized after the popularity of hair-cutting between men of warring classes came to a head with the assault of one individual in the library during daylight hours. The incident resulted in the expulsion of the ring leader; which was protested by fellow students. The faculty, concerned with what they saw as the general decline in good conduct of the students, endeavored to intervene. According to the 1906 Michiganensian students felt that these issues, as student issues, should be dealt with through self-government and the Student Council was elected. The Council is first mentioned in the September 1907 minutes of the Regent's Proceedings as, "men elected by the body of students to secure the wise management of their affairs." The Regents also commend them on stopping the "silly and sometimes dangerous amusement of hair-cutting," among other reforms.
The council moved toward formal organization when it successfully petitioned the Regents for a budget of $150 for the 1912-1913 school year. Early on, the government went through several reincarnations including the Student Senate in 1938 and the Student Legislature circa 1946.
On December 8th and 9th 1954, students voted 5,102 to 1,451 to restructure the student government and asked the Regents to officially recognize the organization. At their December 1954 meeting, the Regents agreed to give the Student Government Council (SGC), as it was to be known, a two-year trial period. The first meeting of the SGC was held in March of 1955 where an eighteen member Council was approved with the constitution of the Student Council serving as a temporary constitution during the trial period. In 1957, the Regents approved the SGC as the, "official and authoritative voice of the University student community." The SGC was given the power to recognize student organizations; a power that had previously belonged to the University Senate Committee on Student Affairs.
Following a period of questioned voting practices and accusations of money mishandling; the SGC's reputation was in tatters amongst students and administration alike. Widespread call for reform resulted in the Central Student Judiciary Committee's January 21, 1976 decision to dissolve the SGC and to establish a new, restructured entity in its place to be called the Michigan Student Assembly (MSA). The Regents officially recognized MSA as the new student government at their September 1976 meeting.
See also the Michigan Student Assembly Record Group (1976 -- Present).
The records encompass a broad range of documents from successive student government agencies including the Student Council, Student Legislature and Student Senate. Included are minutes, petitions, election materials and results, financial records, and correspondence. The most extensive records are those dating from 1960 on. Topical files from that period include reports on university housing, classified research, campus security, minority affairs, and the University Cellar. Included also are the minutes of the Liang Study Committee (1953/1954) and reports from the Office of Student Affairs on housing and student conduct (1966-1969).
Subjects:
African Americans--Michigan.; University of Michigan. Laing Student Committee.; University of Michigan. Student Council.; University of Michigan. Student Government Council.; University of Michigan. Student Legislature.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.; University of Michigan. Student Senate.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Michigan Union.; University of Michigan. Student Government Council.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1951-1960.; Voting.
Contributors:
Laing, Lionel Hassell.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Minutes
  - Student Council October 1912-January 1915 (Box 1)
  - Student Legislature 1946-1953, 2 volumes (Box 1)
  - Laing Study Committee 1953-1954 (Box 1)
    (committee that proposed formation of the Student Government Council)
  - Student Government Council Board in Review 1955-1959 (Box 1)
  - Student Government Council Review Committee 1957 (Box 1)
  - Student Government Council
    - March 18 1955-June 1959, 5 volumes (Box 1)
      (two variant versions of volume 1, one includes minutes of the SGC Steering Committee, January-March 1955)
    - July 1959-June 1965, 6 volumes (Box 2)
    - July 1965-August 1972, 7 volumes (Box 3)
    - September 1972-January 1976, 4 volumes (Box 4)
- Records
  - Compiled Code of SGC 1972-1974 (Box 4)
  - Personal Correspondence (in individual binders) of SGC presidents
    - Douglas Brook November 1964-March 1965 (Box 4)
    - Thomas Brown March 1963-November 1963 (Box 4)
    - Gerry Cunningham March 1965-March 1966 (Box 4)
    - Richard Nohl March 1961-March 1962 (Box 4)
    - Thomas Smithson, March 1964-Octobere 1964 (Box 4)
    - Steven Stockmeyer April 1962-March 1963 (Box 4)
  - Student Senate Petitions 1940, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Student Senate Election Returns 1940 (Box 5)
  - Student Senate Papers 1938-1941, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Student Affairs Committee Papers 1950, 1953-1954, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Student Government Council
    - Papers 1954-1959, 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Elections
      - 1972-1975, 5 folders (Box 5)
      - Ballot Counting Program (Box 5)
    - Finances 1972-1975, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Michigan Daily Clippings 1955-1957, 6 folders (Box 5)
    - Student Advisory Boards to the Administrative Officers (Box 5)
    - Miscellanea (Box 5)
- Administrative Files
  - Student Government Council committee records 1960-1968, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Bylaws 1968 (Box 5)
  - Operating procedures 1969-1970 (Box 5)
  - Appointments (Box 5)
  - Officers' reports 1972 (Box 5)
  - Space allocation materials (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous 1967-1971 (Box 5)
  - Presidents' files
    - Martin Scott 1970-1972 (Box 5)
    - Rebecca Schenk 1971-1972 (Box 5)
    - William Jacobs 1972-1973 (Box 5)
- Topical Files
  - Topical Files
    - Assembly-Panhellenic Spring Rush Study for Student Government Council (Box 5)
    - Black Fund (Box 5)
    - Black Caucus-School of Education (Box 5)
    - Black Christian Nationalist Movement (Box 5)
    - Black Social Workers, Association of (Box 5)
    - Black Student Center Proposed (Box 5)
    - Black Student Union Origin (Box 5)
    - Black Students -- Housing (Box 5)
    - Black Students -- Roster (Box 5)
    - Center for Afro-American and African Studies
      - Administration (Box 5)
      - Budget (Box 5)
      - Courses (Box 5)
      - Newsletter undated (Box 5)
      - Policies (Box 5)
      - Reports (Box 5)
    - Friends of Newsreel (Box 5)
    - Gay Academic Union (Box 5)
    - New World Film Co-op (Box 5)
    - Student organizations-Contact persons (Box 5)
    - Student organizations-Recognition of (Box 5)
    - University Cellar (Box 5)
    - University facilities-use of (Box 5)
    - World University Student Service Fund, Inc. (Box 5)
  - Topical files (Organizations)
    - Michigan Higher Education Students Association 1973 (Box 6)
    - North American Student Cooperative Organization 1972 (Box 6)
    - University of Michigan
      - Office of Special Services and Programs
        - Unit Committee records 1971-1972 (Box 6)
        - Pamphlets 1971-1972 (Box 6)
        - Miscellaneous 1971-1972 (Box 6)
      - Association for Collective Bargaining circa 1972 (Box 6)
      - Engineering Council 1971 (Box 6)
      - Graduate Federation circa 1971 (Box 6)
      - Office of Budgets and Planning, Long Range Planning Committee 1972 (Box 6)
      - Office of Student Organizations circa 1969-1970 (Box 6)
      - Office of Student Services 1970-1971 (Box 6)
      - Program Evaluation Committee 1971-1972, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Student Relations Committee 1968-1969 (Box 6)
      - University Council 1971-1973 (Box 6)
      - University Cellar, Inc.
        - Minutes
          - Board of Directors 1971-1972 (Box 6)
          - Executive Committee 1971-1972 (Box 6)
          - Finance committee 1971-1972 (Box 6)
        - Miscellaneous committees 1971-1972 (Box 6)
        - Miscellaneous 1971-1972 (Box 6)
      - University Housing
        - Housing Policy 1971-1973, 2 folders (Box 6)
        - Rate committee report for University Apartment facilities (Box 6)
        - Miscellaneous, circa1969-1972, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - University Judiciary
        - University Judiciary System 1969-1971, 2 folders (Box 6)
        - Committee on a Permanent University Judiciary 1970-1971, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Other Universities
      - Eastern Michigan University 1970-1972 (Box 6)
      - Illinois, University of 1972 (Box 6)
      - Iowa, University of 1970 (Box 6)
      - Michigan State University circa 1968 (Box 6)
      - Minnesota, University of 1972 (Box 6)
      - Southern California, University of 1970 (Box 6)
      - Miscellaneous Universities (Box 6)
  - Topical Files 1967-1974
    - Classified Research
      - Papers 1971-1972, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Report of the Senate Assembly Committee on Research Policies 1972 (Box 7)
    - Campus Security
      - Papers 1970-1972 (Box 7)
      - Report of the University Police-Relations Committee 1972 (Box 7)
    - University Services
      - Miscellaneous 1970-1972 (Box 7)
      - Report of the Student Affairs Counseling (Box 7)
      - Office on Satelliting of Student Service 1970 (Box 7)
    - Student Government Funding 1967-1971 (Box 7)
    - Ombudsman Service 1971 (Box 7)
    - Board of Regents 1970 (Box 7)
    - Student Conduct 1967-1972, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Steering Committee 1972-1973 (Box 7)
    - Athletics 1972 (Box 7)
    - Teaching Fellow Survey 1969-1970 (Box 7)
    - National Students Lobby 1972-1973 (Box 7)
    - Davis, Michael Reports and speeches 1968-1970 (Box 7)
    - Students for a Democratic Society 1970 (Box 7)
    - Minority Affairs 1970-1972, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Food and Drug Store Survey Report No. 2 circa 1972 (Box 7)
    - Residential College Review Committee Report 1972 (Box 7)
    - Student Involvement in the LSA Department 1972 (Box 7)
  - Flyers 1971-1972 (Box 7)
  - Election materials 1970-1972, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - News Releases. 1969-1972, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Lists of members of various organizations (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous 1967-1974, undated, 6 folders (Box 7)
  - Topical Files 1965-1969
    (Including Earlier and Later Materials)
    - Ad Hoc Committee on the New Degree 1969 (Box 8)
    - Allen, Redoix, Executive V.P. SGC 1974 (Box 8)
    - All-University Congress 1957 (Box 8)
    - Annual reports 1958-1966 (Box 8)
    - Apartment-shortage in Ann Arbor, student papers 1965-1966 (Box 8)
    - Bail fund policy 1968-1972 (Box 8)
    - Black Action Movement (BAM) 1970 (Box 8)
    - Black Action Movement (BAM) strike 1970-1971 (Box 8)
    - Block ticket sales policy 1968 (Box 8)
      (Hill Auditorium)
    - Budget proposals 1966-1976 (Box 8)
    - Center for the Study of Higher Education 1969 (Box 8)
      (Study of SACUA Executive Committees)
    - Cinema Guild 1950-1963, 1967, 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Classified Research at the University of Michigan January 1968 (Box 8)
    - Commission to Study Student Governance 1974-1975 (Box 8)
    - Committee members 1978 (Box 8)
    - Consumer's handbook proposal 1978 (Box 8)
    - Consumer report #1 1969 (Box 8)
    - Course Evaluation 1967-1968 (Box 8)
    - Course Evaluation Project 1977-1978 (Box 8)
    - Course Evaluation Project: Business Administration 1978 (Box 8)
    - Course Evaluation Project: Engineering,1978 (Box 8)
    - Course Evaluation Project: LSA 1978 (Box 8)
    - Course Evaluation Project: School of Natural Resources 1978 (Box 8)
    - Credit Union Co-op Housing Committee 1970 (Box 8)
    - Curriculum Committee Minutes 1968-1969 (Box 8)
    - Davis Reports on Student Government 1968-1969 (Box 8)
    - Demonstration rules 1967 (Box 8)
    - Disruption rules 1968 (Box 8)
    - Draft referendum 1966 (Box 8)
    - Elections, miscellaneous and clippings 1955-1958 (Box 8)
    - Elections systems evaluation (Hare System) 1958-1962 (Box 8)
    - Evaluation committee 1956-1957 (Box 8)
    - Ex officio members 1960 (Box 8)
    - Financial Report July 1974-June 1975 (Box 8)
    - Financial statements
      - 1965-1967 (Box 8)
      - 1974 (Box 8)
    - Financial survey 1965 (Box 8)
    - Fraternities 1963-1967 (Box 8)
    - Gay. Liberation Front 1970 (Box 8)
    - Grievances 1964 (Box 8)
    - Health Insurance 1956-1975, 17 folders (Box 8)
    - Health Service annual report 1973-1974 (Box 8)
    - Health Service study committee report 1968, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Hollenshead reports 1966-1967 (Box 9)
      (student papers on University-Community matters)
    - Homecoming Football Game 1971 (Box 9)
      (student control of halftime shows)
    - House Un-American Activities Committee (university subpoena), clippings 1966 (Box 9)
    - Housing problems 1965-1968, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Intramurals 1969 (Box 9)
    - Kellman, F. Scott, President 1977 (Box 9)
    - King, Jr., Martin Luther (memorial fund) 1969 (Box 9)
    - Legal Counsel reports 1972 (Box 9)
    - Legal Counsel retainer agreement 1972 (Box 9)
    - Legal Services 1968-1971 (Box 9)
    - Life insurance 1970-1973, 3 folders (Box 9)
    - Literature, Science, and the Arts (LS&A) Student Government (Box 9)
    - Loyalty oaths 1958-1961 (Box 9)
    - Mail vote (conducted in summer 1975) (Box 9)
    - Membership 1955-1960 (Box 9)
      (newspaper photos)
    - Membership, student organizations 1962-1968 (Box 9)
    - Membership tribunal 1963-1969 (Box 9)
    - National Student Association (NSA)-CIA connections 1967 (Box 9)
    - Newsletters 1967-1969 (Box 9)
    - Newsletters, "Student Action," 1971 (Box 9)
    - Non-academic discipline 1966-1968 (Box 9)
    - Office of Student Affairs (Box 9)
      - General 1966 (Box 9)
      - Acting Vice-President's report 1968-1969 (Box 9)
      - Advisory committee on housing 1967-1969 (Box 9)
      - Study committee 1961-1962, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Study committee reports 1962 (Box 9)
      - Vice-President search 1970 (Box 9)
    - Office of Student Organizations 1967 (Box 9)
    - Officers' reports 1972 (Box 9)
    - Operating procedures 1968-1970 (Box 9)
    - "Operation Abolition" (movie on student protest) 1961-1962 (Box 9)
    - Opportunity awards 1971-1973 (Box 9)
    - Police-University relations 1968-1969 (Box 9)
    - Political activity recess 1970 (Box 9)
    - Regents
      - Closed meeting policy 1970 (Box 9)
      - Student papers 1968 (Box 9)
    - Reserve Officer Training Corps (ROTC) 1969 (Box 9)
    - Rose Bowl 1965 (Box 9)
      (student letters criticizing tour arrangements)
    - Strike Policy 1970 (Box 9)
    - Student conduct regulations 1970 (Box 9)
    - Student movement 1966-1967 (Box 9)
    - "SGC Needs You," 1972 (Box 9)
    - Student Organizations
      - Board 1973-1976, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Director 1974-1975 (Box 9)
      - Regulations 1963-1966, 1970, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - University Bookstore
      - General 1969-1972 (Box 9)
      - Articles of Incorporation and By-Laws 1969-1970 (Box 9)
      - Campaign to organize 1969 (Box 9)
    - University Regulations
      - Student conduct 1959-1967 (Box 9)
      - Pamphlets 1954, 1961 undated (Box 9)
    - Voting privileges 1955-1962 (Box 9)
    - Voting registration 1969-1971 (Box 9)
    - WCBN-Radio expansion 1970 (Box 9)
    - Women students' residence requirements 1966-1967 (Box 9)
    - Year-round operation (trimester schedule)
      - General 1962-1966 (Box 9)
      - Clippings (Box 9)
      - Commission report 1961 (Box 9)
  - Photographs (Box 9)
  - Clippings, ballots, etc. (Folder 1)
- Scrapbooks
  - Scrapbooks Concerning Inter-Fraternity Council 1953-1956 (Box 10)
  - Scrapbooks compiled by the Student Government Council
    - 1955-1960, 1968-1975, 6 volumes (Box 10)
    - 1965-1975 (Volume 1)
    - 1970-1971 (Volume 2)
    - 1973-1975 (Volume 3)
- Presidential Photographs
  - Unidentified (Box 11)
  - March 1955-October 1964 (Box 11)
  - March 1965-March 1966 (Box 11)
  - March 1967-March 1972 (Box 11)
  - May 1973-January 1976 (Box 11)